<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of a religious priest vnto his father: exhorting him to the perfect forsaking of the world.</title>
            <author>Southwell, Robert, Saint, 1561?-1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22968.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">72799859</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 72799859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2229:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of a religious priest vnto his father: exhorting him to the perfect forsaking of the world.</title>
                  <author>Southwell, Robert, Saint, 1561?-1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Fr. Garnet's second press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title taken from first page of text.</note>
                  <note>Publication data suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B¹².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks t.p. and all after page 46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fathers --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:184123:1"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE OF A RELIGIOVS PRIEST VNTO his father: exhorting him to the perfect forſaking of the world.</head>
            <head type="sub">TO THE WORSHIPFVL his very good father, R. S. his dutifull ſonne R. S. wiſheth all happines.</head>
            <p>IN childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of former ages, it hath bene thought ſo behofull a point of dewty to theire parents, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence by ſeruiceable offices, in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence by other affectuall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, to yeld proofe of their thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mindes, that neither any child could omitte it, without touch of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184123:2"/>vngratfulnes, nor the parents for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare it without iuſt diſpleaſure. But now we are falne into ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitye of times, and the violence of hereſy hath ſo croſſed the courſe, both of vertew &amp; nature, that their ingraffed lawes, neuer infringed by the moſt ſauage &amp; brute creatures, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not of Gods people without pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill be obſerued. I am not of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall a kind, of ſo wilde educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſo vnchriſtian a ſpirite, as not to remember the roote out of which I braunched, or to forget my ſecondary maker and auctor of my being: It is not the careleſnes of a colde affection, nor the want of a dew and reuerent reſpect, that hath made me ſuch a ſtranger to my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue home, and ſo ſlacke in defray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the debt of a thankfull minde, but onely the iniquity of our daies,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184123:2"/>that maketh my preſence perillous and the diſcharge of my dewty an occaſion of daunger. I was loth to enforce an vnwelcome courteſy vp on any, or by ſeming officious, to become offenſiue, deeming it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to let time digeſt the feare, that my return into the realme had bred in my kindred, then apruptly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude my ſelfe, to purchaſe theire anger, whoſe good will I ſo highly eſteemed. I neuer doubted, but that the beliefe, which to all my frendes by deſcent and petegree is in maner hereditary, framed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a righte perſwaſion of my preſent calling, not ſuffering them to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their cenſures of me, by the vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termes, and odious Epitheetes, wherwith hereſy hath ſought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>credite my function, but rather by the reuerence of ſo worthy a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184123:3"/>and the ſacred doome of all former ages. Yet becauſe I might verye eaſely perceiue by apparent coniectures, that many were more willing to heare of me, then from me, and readier to praiſe, then to vſe my endeuours, I haue hitherto bridled my deſire to ſee them, with the care and ieloſy of their ſaftye, &amp; baniſhing my ſelfe from the ſent of my cradle, in my owne country I haue liued like a forreiner, finding emong ſtrangers that, which in my neereſt bloode I preſumed not to ſeeke. But now conſidering, that delay may haue qualified feare, &amp; knowing my perſon onely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port daunger to others, and my per ſwaſion to none but to my ſelfe, I thought it highe time to vtter my ſincere and duetifull minde, and to open a vent to my zealous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184123:3"/>which I haue ſo long ſmothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſuppreſſed in ſilence. For not onely the originall lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, written in all childrens harts, and deriued from the bowells and breſtes of their mothers, is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſoliciter vrging me in your be halfe, but the ſouereigne decree e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted by the father of heauen, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by his ſonne, and daily repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by inſtincte of the holy ghoſt, bindeth euery child in the dew of Chriſtianitye, to tender the eſtate and welfare of his parentes, and is a motiue, that alloweth no excuſe, but of neceſſity preſſeth to perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of dewty. Nature by grace is not aboliſhed, but perfited, not murdered, but manured, neither are her impreſſions quite raſed, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled, but ſuted to the colours of faith and vertew. And if her affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184123:4"/>be ſo forcible, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hell where rancour and deſpite chiefly reigneth, &amp; all feeling of goodnes is ouerwhelmed in malice, they mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the rich glutton by experience of his owne miſery to carry the leſſe enuy to his kinred: how much more in the Church of God, where grace quickneth, charity enflameth, and natures good inclinations are abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by ſupernaturall giftes, ought the duety of piety to preuaile. And who but more merciles then dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned creatures, could ſee their dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt frendes plunged in the like pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and not to be wounded with deepe remorſe of their lamentable and imminent hazardes? If in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding a mortall enemy wroung and tortured with deadly pangues, the tougheſt harte ſofteneth with ſome ſorow: If the moſt frozen and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184123:4"/>fierce minde cannot but thawe and melte with pity, euen when it ſeeth the worſt miſcrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuffer his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued torments: how much leſſe can the hart of a childe, conſider thoſe that bredd him into this world, to be in the fall to farr more bitter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and not bleed with griefe of their vncomfortable caſe. Surely for my owne parte, though I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge not the prerogatiue of the beſt diſpoſition, yet am I not of ſo harſhe and curriſh an humour, but that it is a continuall corraſiue, and croſſe vnto me, that wheras my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours haue reclaimed many fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the brincke of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I haue bene leaſt able to employ them, where they were moſt dew, &amp; barred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affordinge to my deereſt frendes, that which hath ben eagerly ſought and beneficially obtained of mere
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184123:5"/>ſtrangers. Who hath more intereſt in the grape then he that planted the vine? who more right to the cropp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that ſowed the corne? or how can the child owe ſo greate ſeruice to any, as to him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he is indebted vnto for his very life and being? With yong Tobye I haue trauailed farre, and brought home a freight of ſpirituall ſubſtance, to enrich you, &amp; medicinable receites againſt your ghoſtlye maladyes. I haue with Eſau after long toile in purſuing a painfull chaſe, returned with ſuch pray as you were wonte to loue, deſiring therby to procure your bleſſing. I haue in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall famine of all true and Chriſtian food, with Ioſeph prepared abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the bread of Angells, for the repaſt of your ſoule. And now my deſire is that my drugges may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184123:5"/>cure you, my pray delight you, and my prouiſion feed you, by whom I haue bene cured, delighted, and fedd my ſelfe, that your courteſies may in parte be counteruailed, and my ducty in ſome ſorte performed. Deſpiſe not good Sir the youth of your ſonne, neither deeme that god meaſureth his endouments by num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of yeeres. Hoary ſenſes are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten couched vnder greene lockes, and ſome are riper in the ſpringe, then others in the Autumne of their age. God choſe not Iſaï him ſelfe, nor his eldeſt ſonne, but yong Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to conquere Golias and to rule his people. Not the moſt aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but Daniel the moſt innocent infant deliuered Suzanna from the iniquity of the iudges: and Chriſt at twelue yeares of age, was found in the temple queſtioning with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184123:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>graueſt Doctors. A true Elias can conceiue, that a little cloude may caſt a large &amp; abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant ſhower, and the ſcripture teacheth vs, that God reuealeth to little ones that which he concealeth from the wiſeſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. His truth is not abaſed by the minority of the ſpeaker, who out of the mouthes of infantes &amp; ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges can perfit his praiſes. Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy was yong, and yet a principall paſtour. S. Ihon not olde and yet an Apoſtle, yea and the Angels by appearing in youthfull ſemblances, giue vs a pregnant proofe, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glorious giftes may be ſhrouded vnder tender ſhapes. All which I alledge, not to claime any priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſurmounting the rate of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all habilities, but to auoid all touch of preſumption in aduiſing my el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſeing that it hath the warrant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184123:6"/>of ſcripture, the teſtimony of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, &amp; ſufficient groundes both in grace and nature. There is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity in the degrees of our carnall conſanquinity, and the preminence appertaineth to you, as ſuperiour ouer your childes body. Yet if you conſider our alliance in the chiefe portion, I meane our foule, which diſcerneth man from inferiour cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, we are of equall proximity to our heauenly father, both deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of the ſame parent, and no other diſtance in our degrees, but that you are the elder brother. In this ſenſe doth the ſcripture ſaye, Call not any father vpon earth, for one is your father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Seing therfore that your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority is founded vpon fleſh and blood, which are in maner but the barke and rine of a man, and our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184123:7"/>equality vppon the ſoule, which is mans maigne ſubſtance, thinke it I praye you no diſhonour to your age, or diſparagement to your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, If with all humility I offer my aduiſe vnto you. One man cannot be perfect in all faculties, neither is it a diſgrace to the goldſmith, if he be ignorant of the milleners trade. Many are deepe lawiers and yett ſhallowe Diuines, manye verye de liuer in feates of the body, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in externall complementes, yet litle experimented in matters of their ſoule and farre to ſeeke in religious actions. I haue ſtudied &amp; practiſed theſe many yeeres ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall phiſicke, acquainting my ſelfe with the beating and temper of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery pulſe, &amp; trauailing in the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny of the maladies &amp; medicines in cident vnto ſoules. If therfore I pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184123:7"/>you the fruits of my long ſtudies and make you a preſent of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, I hope you will conſtrue it rather as a duetifull parte, then any point of preſumption. He may be a father to the ſoule, that is a ſonne to the body, and requite the benefit of his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall life, by reuiuing his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from a ſpirituall death. And to this effect did chriſt ſay thes words: my mother, and brethren are they, that do the will of my father which is in heauen: Vpon which place S. Climacus ſhewing to what kinred a Chriſtian ought chiefly to relye, draweth this diſcourſe. Let him be thy father, that both can and will lay his labour to disburden thee of thy packe of ſinnes. Let holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction be thy mother, to depure thee from thy ordure and filth. Let him be thy brother, that wilbe both
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184123:8"/>thy partner and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peditour to paſſe and perfite thy race towardes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Take the memory of death for thy perpetuall pheere, and vnſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſpouſe. Lett thy children be bitter ſighes of a ſorowfull harte, and poſſeſſe thy body as thy bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Faſten thy frendſhippe with the Angelicall powers, with which if thou cloſeſt in familiar affiance, they will be patrones vnto thee in thy finall paſſage. This (ſaieth he) is the generation &amp; kinred of thoſe that ſeeke God. Such a father as this Sainte ſpeaketh of, maye you haue of your owne ſonne, to enter you farther in the fore recited affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Of which happely it was a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preſage, aboding the future euent, that euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my infancy you were wont in merime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to call me fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, R. which is the cuſtumary ſtile
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184123:8"/>now allotted to my preſent eſtate.</p>
            <p>Now therfore to ioine iſſue, and to come to the principall drifte of my diſcourſe, moſt humbly &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly I am to beſech you, that both in reſpect of the honour of God, your duty to his Church, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of your children, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres of your owne ſoule, you wold ſeriouſly conſider the termes you ſtand in, &amp; way your ſelfe in a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ballance, taking for your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſe the iudgementes of God. Take heede in time, that the word <hi>Thecel</hi> writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of olde againſt <hi>Balta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> &amp; interpreted by <hi>Daniel, Dan. 5.</hi> be not verified in you, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was: <hi>you haue bene poiſed in the ſcoale, and found of to lighte weight.</hi> Remember that you are in the waining, and the date of your pilgrimage is well nere expired, &amp;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184123:9"/>now it behooueth you to looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes your country. Your force languiſheth, your ſenſes impaire, &amp; your body droupeth, and on euery ſide the ruinous cottage of your faint &amp; feeble fleſh, thretneth fall. And hauing ſo many herbingers of death to premoniſhe you of your end, how can you but prepare for ſo dredfull a ſtranger. The yonge may dye quickly, but the olde can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue long. The yong mens life by caſualty may be abridged, but the olde mens by no phiſicke can be long adiourned: and therfore if greene yeres ſometimes muſt think of the graue, the thoughtes of ſere age ſhould continually dwel in the ſame. The prerogatiue of infancie is innocency, of childhoode reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, of manhood maturity, and of age wiſdome. And ſeeing that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184123:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the chiefe properties of wiſdome are, to be mindfull of things paſſed carefull of thinges preſent, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident of thinges to come, vſe now the priuiledge of natures talent to the benefitte of your ſoule, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure hereafter to be wiſe in weldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and watchfull in foreſight of future harmes. To ſerue the world you are now vnhable, and though you were hable you haue litle cauſe to be willing, ſeeing that it neuer gaue you but an vnhappy welcome a hurtfull entertainment, and now doth abandon you with an vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate farewell. You haue long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in a field of flint, which could bring you nothing forth, but a crop of cares, and affliction of ſpirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding your labours with remorſe and affording for your gaine eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall domages. It is now more then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184123:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>a ſeaſonable time time, to alter the courſe of ſo vnthriuing a husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry, and to enter into the field of Gods Church, in which ſowing the ſeeds of repentant ſorow, and watering them with the teares of humble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, you may reape a more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall harueſt, &amp; gather the fruits of euerlaſting comforte. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I pray you, that your ſpring is ſpent, and your ſomer ouerpaſt: you are now arriued to the fall of leafe, yea and winter colours haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtained your hoary head. Be not careles (ſaieth <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi>) though our louing Lorde beare long with offenders. for the longer he ſtaieth not finding amendment, the ſorer will he ſcourge when he cometh to ludgement. and his patience in ſo long expecting, is onely to lend vs reſpite to repent, not any way to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184123:10"/>enlarge vs leiſure to ſinne. He that is toſſed with varietye of ſtormes, &amp; cannot come to his deſired port, maketh not much way, but is much tormoiled: So he that hath paſſed many yeeres, and purchaſed little profitte, hath had a long being, but a ſhorte life. for life is more to be meaſured by merittes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of daies, ſeeing that moſt men by many daies do but procure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deathes, and others in a ſhorte ſpace attein the life of infinite ages. What is the body without the ſoule but a corrupte carcaſe: and what the ſoule without God, but a ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of ſinne. If God be the way, the life, and the truth, he that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without him, ſtrayeth: he that liueth without him, dieth: and he that is not taught by him, erreth. Well ſaieth <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> that God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184123:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>is our trew and chiefeſt life, from whome the reuolting is falling, to whome the returninge is riſing, in whom the ſtaying is ſure ſtanding. God is he, from whom to depart is to dye, to whom to repaire is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue, in whome to dwell is to liue. Be not you therfore of thoſe, that beginne not to liue, vntill they be ready to dye, &amp; then after a foes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, come to craue of God a frends entertainment. Some thincke to ſnatch heauen in a moment, which the beſt ſcarce atteined in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of many yeeres. and when they haue glutted them ſelues with worldly delites, they would iumpe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Diues his diet to Lazarus croun, and from the ſeruice of Satan to the ſolacy of a Saint. But be you well aſſured, that god is not ſo penurious of frendes, as to hold him ſelfe and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184123:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>his kingdome ſalable for the refuſe and reuerſion of theire liues, who haue ſacrificed the principall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to his enemies, and their owne brutiſhe appetites, then onely cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to offend, when hability of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending is taken from them. True it is, that a theefe may be ſaued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, and mercy found at the laſt gaſpe. But well ſaieth ſaint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that though it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yett is it ſcarce credible, that his death ſhould find fauour, whoſe whole life hath earned wrath, and that his repentance ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, that more for feare of hell, and loue of him ſelfe, then for loue of God or lothſomnes of ſinne, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for mercy. Wherfore good Sir make no longer delayes, but being ſo neere the breaking vpp of your mortall houſe, take time before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitye
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184123:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſatisfie Gods Iuſtice. Though you ſuffered the bud to be blaſted, &amp; the flower to fade, thogh you permitted the fruite to be peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the leaues to drye vp, yea though you let the bougheswither, and the body of your tree growe to decaye: yett alas keepe life in the roote, for feare leaſt the wholle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fuell for hell fire. for ſurely wherſoeuer the tree falleth, there ſhall it be, whether it be to ſouth or north, heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or hell, &amp; ſuch ſap as it bringeth ſuch fruit ſhal it euer bear. Death hath already filed from you the better part of your naturall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hath lefte you now to the lees and remiſſailes of your weariſh and dyinge dayes: the remainder wherof, as it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be long, ſo doth it warne you ſpeedilye to ranſome your former loſſes. For what is age
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184123:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>but the calendes of death, and what importeth your preſent weaknes, but an earneſt of your approching diſſolution? You are now impath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your finall voiage, and not far of from the ſtint and period of your courſe: and therfore be not diſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied of ſuch appurtenances as are behoofull in ſo perplexed and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous a iorney. Death in it ſelfe is very fearefull, but much more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in regard of the iudgement that it ſummoneth vs vnto. If you were layed on your departing bed, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with the heauy load of your former trespaſſes, and goared with the ſting and pricke of a feſtered conſcience: If you felt the crampe of death wreſting your hart ſtringes &amp; ready to make the rufull diuorce betweene body and ſoule: If you lay panting for breath, and ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184123:13"/>in a colde and fatall ſweat, weried with ſtrugling againſt your deadly panges: O how much wold you giue for an hower of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at what rate woulde you valew a dayes contrition. Then worldes would be worthles in reſpecte of a litle reſpitte. A ſhorte truce would ſeeme more pretious, then the trea ſures of Empires. nothing would be ſo much eſteemed as a trice of time, which now by monethes and yeeres is lauiſhly miſpent. O how deeply would it wound your hart, when looking backe into your life you conſidered many faultes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and not confeſſed, manye good workes omitted and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, your ſeruice to God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and not performed. How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolable were your caſe, your frends being fled, your ſenſes frigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184123:13"/>your thoughtes amazed, your memory decaied, your whole mind agaſt, and no partable to performe that it ſhould, but onely your guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſcience peſtered with ſinne, that would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually vpbreid you with moſt bitter accuſations. what woulde you thinke when ſtripped out of your mortall weed, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both out of the ſeruice &amp; houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome of this world, you were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to enter into vncouth &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge pathes, &amp; with vnknowen and vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly company to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented before a moſt ſeuere iudge, carying in your owne conſcience your enditement written, and a perfitte regiſter of all your miſdeedes: when you ſhould ſee him prepared to paſſe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vpon you, againſt whom you had tranſgreſſed, and the ſame to be your vmpier, whom by ſo many
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184123:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces you had made your enemy: When not onely the Deuells, but euen the Angells ſhould pleade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and your ſelfe maugre your will be your ſharpeſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. What would you do in theſe dredfull exigentes? When you ſaw that gaſtly dungeon &amp; huge golfe of hell, breaking out with moſt fear full flames: Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſaw the wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping &amp; gnaſhing of teeth, the rage of thoſe helliſh monſters, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the place, the rigour of the paine, the terrour of the company, and the eternity of all theſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, would you then thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſe, that would daly in ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters, and idly play away the time allotted to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theſe intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable calamities? would you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> account it ſecure, to nurſe in your boſome ſo many ſerpents as ſinnes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184123:14"/>or to foſter in your ſoule ſo manye malicious accuſers as mortal faltes? Would yo not then thinke one life to little to do penance for ſo many iniquities, euery one wherof were enough to caſt you into thoſe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and vnſpeakable torments? Why then do you not at the leaſt deuote that ſmall remnant and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſage of theſe your latter dayes, procuring to make an attonement with God and to free your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from ſuch corruption, as by your ſchiſme and fall hath crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. Thoſe very eies that read this diſcourſe, and that very vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that conceiueth it, ſhalbe ſigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; certaine witneſſes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed thinges. In your owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall you experience thoſe ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agonies, and in your ſoule ſhall you feelinglye finde thoſe terrible
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184123:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>feares, yea and your preſent eſtate is in danger of the deepeſt harmes, if you doe not the ſooner recouer your ſelfe into the folde and family of Gods Church. What haue you gotten by being ſo long cuſtomer to the world, but falſe ware ſutable to the ſhoppe of ſuch a marchant, whoſe traficke is toile, whoſe welth traſhe, and whoſe gaine miſerye? what intereſt haue you reaped, that maye equall your decrementes in grace and vertew, or what coulde you find in a vale of teares parage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the fauour of God, with the loſſe wherof you were contented to buy it: You cannot be now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigled with the paſſions of youth, which making a partiall eſtimate of thinges ſette no diſtance betweene counterfeite and currant. For they are now worn out of force by tract
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184123:15"/>of time, or fallen in reproofe by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of their folly. It cannot be feare that leadeth you amiſſe, ſeeing it were to vnfitting a thing, that the craua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cowardice of fleſh &amp; blood, ſhould daunte the proweſſe of an intelligent perſon, who by his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can-not but diſcerne, how much more cauſe there is to feare God then man, &amp; to ſtand in more awe of perpetuall, then of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall penalties. If it be an vngroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded preſumption of the mercy of God, and the hope of his aſſiſtance at the laſt plunge, (the ordinarye lure of the Deuell to reclaime ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from the purſuite of vertew) it is to palpable a colluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to miſleade a ſound and ſenſed man, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it preuaile with ſicke and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted iudgmentes. Who would rely eternall affaires vppon the gliding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184123:16"/>ſlippernes &amp; running ſtreame of our vncertaine life? or who but one of diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered wittes, would offer fraud to the decipherer of all thoughtes, with whome diſſemble we may to our coſt, but to deceiue him it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. Shall we eſteeme it cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to robbe the time from him and beſtow it on his enemies, who keepeth tale of the leaſt minutes of our life, &amp; will examine in the end how eche moment hath bene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied. It is a prepoſterous pollicy in any wiſe conceit, to fight againſt God till our weapons be blunted, our forces conſumed, our limmes impotent, and our beſt ſpent, and then when we fall for faintnes, and haue fought our ſelues almoſt dead to preſume of his mercy, the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds both of his ſacred body, ſo often rubbed and renued by our ſinnes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184123:16"/>and euery parcell of our owne ſo ſundry and diuerſe waies abuſed, being ſo many whetſtones and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiues to edge and exaſperat his reuenge againſt vs. It were a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge peece of art, and a very exorbitant courſe, while the ſhippe is ſound, the Pilote well, the ſailers ſtrong, the gale fauourable, and the Sea calme, to lye idle at rode, burning ſo ſeaſonable wether: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhip leaked, the Pilot were ſick, the Mariners faint, the ſtormes boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and the Sea a tormoile of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious ſurges, then to lanch forth, to hoiſe vp ſailes, and to ſet out for a voiage into farre countries. Yett ſuch is the skill of theſe euening re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters, who though in the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of helth, and in the perfitte vſe of reaſon, they cannot reſolue to cut the gables and weigh the anc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184123:17"/>that with-hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from God, neuertheleſſe they feed them ſelues with a ſtrong perſwaſion, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſenſes are aſtonied, their witts diſtracted, their vnderſtanding duſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and both the body and minde racked &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with the throbs and gripes of a mortall ſicknes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſooth will they thincke of the weightieſt matters, &amp; become ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Saintes, when they are ſcarce able to behaue them ſelues, like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures. If neither the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, ciuill, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that a man periſhed in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould make any teſtament or bequeſte of his temporall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, being then preſumed to be leſſe then a man: how can he that is amated with the inward garboils of an vnſetled conſcience, diſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the wringing fittes of his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184123:17"/>dying fleſhe, maimed in all his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, &amp; circled in with ſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge encombrances, be thought of dew diſcretion to diſpoſe of his chiefeſt iewell, which is his ſoule, and to diſpatch the wholle menage of all eternity, &amp; of the treaſures of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in ſo ſtormy and ſhorte a ſpurt. No no they that will loyter in ſeed time, and beginne onely to ſowe, when others reape: They that will riotte out their health, &amp; caſt theire accountes when they can ſcarcely ſpeake: They that will ſlumber out the day &amp; enter their iorney when the light doth faile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let them blame their owne folly, if they dye in debt, and eternall beggers, and fall hedlong into the lapſe of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perdition. Let ſuch harken to <hi>S. Ciprians</hi> leſſon. Let (ſaieth he) the greeuouſnes of our ſore, be the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184123:18"/>ſure of our ſorrowe. Lett a deepe wounde haue deepe and dilligent cure. Lett no mans contrition be leſſe then his crime. Thinkeſt thou that our Lord can be ſo ſoone ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with perfidious words thou haſt denied, whom leſſe then thy patrimony thou haſt eſteemed, whoſe temple with ſacriligious cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruption thou haſt defiled. Thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou eaſely to recouer his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, whome thou haſt auouched not to be thy Maſter? We muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt inſtantly intreat, we muſt paſſe the day in mourning, the night in watching, &amp; weeping, our wholl time in plainfull lamentinge. We muſt fall proſtrate vpon the ground humbling our ſelues in ſackclothe and aſhes. And hauing loſt the gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, we ſhould be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willinge to be clothed with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184123:18"/>hauing farſed our ſtomackes with the viande of the Deuell, we ſhould now deſire to faſt from all earthly food. We ſhould ply good workes to purge our offences, we ſhould be liberall in almes to auoid the death of our ſoules, that Chriſt may receiue, that the perſecutour would haue ſpoiled, neither ought that patrimony to be kept or phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, with which a man hath bene enſnared &amp; vanquiſhed. Not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort ſighe will be a ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, nor euery knocke a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to get in. Many cry Lord Lord and are not accepted. The fooliſh Virgins knocked, and were not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Iudas had ſome ſorow and yet dyed deſperate. Forſlowe not ſaieth the holy ghoſt to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God, and linger not of from day to day. for ſodeinly will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184123:19"/>his wrath come, and in the time of reuenge he will deſtroy thee. Lett no man ſoiourne long in his ſinfull ſecuritye, nor poſt ouer his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till feare enforce him vnto it. Lett vs frame our premiſes as we would find our concluſion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to liue as we are deſirous to dye. Shall we offer the mayne crop to the Deuell, and ſet God to glean the reproofe of his harueſt? Shall we gorge the Deuell with our fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt fruites, and turne God to feed on the filthy ſcraps of his leauings? How great a folly were it when a man pineth away in a perillous lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guour, to prouide gorgeous appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, to beſpeake ſumptuous furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and take order for the rearing of ſtately buildings, &amp; neuer think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his owne recouery, to let the diſeaſe take roote within him? were
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184123:19"/>it not the like vanity, for a Prince to dote ſo farre vpon his ſubiecte, as neglecting his owne regalty, to buſy him ſelfe wholly in aduancing his ſeruant? Thus ſaieth <hi>S. Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> do they, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſoule hath ſurfeited with all kind of ſinne and is drenched in the depth of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſeaſes, without any regard therof, labour their wittes in ſetting forth her garment, and in pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the body with all poſſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes. And wheras the ſoule ſhold haue the ſoueraignty, and the body followe the ſway of her direction, ſcruile ſenſes, and lawleſſe appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites do rule her as ſuperiours, and ſhe is made a vaſſall in her owne dominions. What is there ſayeth <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in thy meaneſt nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſaries, that thou wouldeſt not haue good? Thou wouldeſt haue a good
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184123:20"/>houſe, good furniture, good appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, good fare, good cattell, and not ſo much but thy hoſe and thy ſhoes thou wilt ſeek to haue good. Onely thy life and poore ſoule, thy principall charge, and of all other things the moſt worthy to be beſt, thou arte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent ſhould be nought, and ly cancring and ruſting in all kinde of euelles. O vnſpeakable blindnes. can we preferr our ſhoes before our ſoule, refuſing to we are an euell ſhoe, and not caring to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an vgly &amp; deformed ſoule? Alas let vs not ſet ſo litle by that, which God priſed ſo much. Lett vs not rate our ſelues at ſoe baſe a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, being in truth of ſo pereles dignity. If the ſoule be ſuch, that not all the gold and treaſure of the world, nor any thing of leſſe worth then the blood and life of almighty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184123:20"/>God, was able to buy it. If not all the deinties that witt can deuiſe, or heauen and earth afford, but onely Gods owne pretious body was by him deemed a repaſt fitt to feed it. If not all the creatures of this, nor millions of new worldes, if ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more were created, but onely the illimitable goodnes and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye of God can ſatisfie the deſire, and fill the compaſſe and capacity of it, who but of lame iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or peruers will, yea who but of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous mind, and pitiles ſpirite could ſet more by his ſhoes, then he did by his ſoule, or be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to ſuffer ſo noble a paragon, ſo many monethes and yeeres to ly chanel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ordure, &amp; mired in all ſinne. Can we not ſee our ſeruant ſicke, but we allow him a Phiſician, our horſe diſeaſed but we ſend for a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184123:21"/>leach, nor our garment torne, but we will haue one to mend it? and can we ſo much maligne out ſoule, as to let it dye for want of cure, and ſeing it mangled with ſo many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, neuer ſeeke any to reſtore it to the wonted inte grity? Is our ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neerer, our beaſt more pretious, &amp; our coate dearer, then our owne ſoule? If any ſhold call vs Epicures Aetheſtes, rebells vnto God, or mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derers of ſoules, we would take it for an vntollerable reproche, and thinke it a moſt diſgracefull &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious calumniatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to liue like Epicures, to ſinne like Aethiſts to ſtruggle againſt Gods callinges, and like viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rebells to ſcorne his commandements: yea &amp; with dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and damnable wounds, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to ſtab our infortunat ſoules, this we account no contumely, we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184123:21"/>reckon for no diſcreditt, yea rather we regiſter it in the vaunte of our chiefe praiſes. O ye ſonnes of men, how long will you carry this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy hart, aliking vanity, and ſeeking lyes? how long will children loue the follies of infancye, and ſinners runne careleſſe and wilfull to their ruine? Will you keepe your chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the kite, your lambe from the wolfe, your faune fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Dare you not ſuffer a ſpider in your boſome, or a toade to come nere you, &amp; can you neſtle in your ſoule ſo many vipers as vices, and permit it to be ſo long chewed, &amp; weried with the poiſoned iawes, &amp; tuskes of the Deuell? And is our ſoule ſo vaine a ſubſtance as to be had in ſo litle eſteeme? Had Chriſt made ſhipwracke of his wiſdome, or was he in a rage of paſſion when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184123:22"/>a wandering pilgrimme exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him ſelfe from the comfortes of his Godhead, and paſſing three and thirty yeares in paine and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury for the be hoofe of our ſoules? Was he ſurpriſed with a rauing fitt, when in the tragedy of his paſſion ſo bloodily inflicted, and ſo pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently accepted, he made his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as a cloud, to reſolue into ſhou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of innocent blood, and ſuffered the deereſt veines of his hart to be lanced, to giue full iſſue to the price of our ſoules redemption? Or if Chriſt did not erre, nor deeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, when it pleaſed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs with ſo exceſſiue a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, then what ſhould we iudge of our monſtruous abuſe, that ſell our ſoule to the Deuell for euerye vaine delighte, &amp; rather aduenture the hazard therof, then of a ſelye
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184123:22"/>pittance of worldly pelfe. O that a creature of ſo inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable a price, ſhould be in the demaine of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall keepers, and that which is in it ſelfe ſo gracious and amiable, that the Angells and Saintes delite to behold it, (as <hi>S. Chriſoſtome</hi> ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) ſhould by ſinne be faſhioned into ſo lothſome &amp; diſguiſed ſhapes as to become a horrour to heauen, and a ſutely pheere for the fouleſt fiendes. Alas if the care of our own harmes moue vs no more, but that we can ſtill be ſo barbarous to the better portion of our ſelues, lett vs at the leſt feare to iniury an other party, very carefull and ielious ouer it: who will neuer endure ſo deepe an impeachment of his intereſt to paſſe vnreuenged. We muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that our ſoule is not onely a part of vs, but alſo the temple, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184123:23"/>paradiſe, and ſpouſe of Almightye god, by him in baptiſme garniſhed, ſtored, and endowed with moſte graciouſe ornamentes. And how think you, he can brooke, to ſee his temple prophaned, and turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a denne of Deuels, his paradiſe diſplanted, and altered into a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of ſerpentes, his ſpouſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured, and become an adultereſſe to his vtter enemies? Durſt we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch vſage to our Princes, yea or to our farmers daughter? woulde not feare of the lawe, and popular ſhame, diſturne vs from it? And ſhall not the reuerend Maieſtye of almighty God, and the vnrebated iuſtice of his angry ſword, terrifie vs from offering the like to his own ſpouſe? Do we thinke God either ſo impotent that he cannot, ſo baſe and ſottiſh that he will not, or ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184123:23"/>weake witted that he knoweth not how to wreake him ſelfe vpon ſo conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous and daring offenders? Will he ſo neglect and loſe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which of all thinges he clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as his chiefe peculier? Will he that for the ſoules ſake keepeth a reckoninge of our verye heares, which are but the excrementes of her earthly weed, ſee him ſelfe ſo much wronged in the principall, &amp; paſſe it without remo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrance of his iuſt indignation? O deere Sir reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſcripture termeth it a thing full of horrour to fall into the hands of God, who is able to cruſh the proud ſpirittes of the obſtinate, and to make his enemies the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole of his feete. Wraſtle no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt the cries of your owne conſcience, and the forcible inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that God doth ſende you.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:184123:24"/>Embrace his mercy before the time of rigour, &amp; returne to his Church leſt he debarre you his kingdome. He cannot haue God for his father, that refuſeth to profeſſe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church for his mother, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he atchiue to the Church triumphant in heauen, that is not a member of the Church milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here in earth.</p>
            <p>You haue bene alas to long an aliant in the tabernacles of ſinners, and ſtraied to farr from the folde of Gods flocke. Turne now the blaze of your harte towardes the ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary of ſaluation, and the city of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, ſeeking to recompence your wandering ſteppes trodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in error, with a ſwifte gate and zelous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe to Chriſtian perfection, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deming the time becauſe the daies be euell. The full of your ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184123:24"/>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:184123:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:184123:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
